Guide to the John B. Kelly papers AD.MC.058
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
- Publications and writings, 1956-2018
  - Books, 1961-2018 and undated
    - Desert Dispute: galley proofs, volume 1, 2017 (Box 29, Folder 11)
    - Desert Dispute: galley proofs, volume 2, 2017 (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - Desert Dispute: research materials: Persian Gulf Territorial (FCO 8/59), 1967-1969 (Box 29, Folder 13)
    - Desert Dispute: research materials: Persian Gulf. Territorial. Buraimi (FCO 8/60), 1967-1968 (Box 29, Folder 14)
    - Desert Dispute: research materials: Oman...Boundaries (FCO 8/586), 1967-1968 (Box 29, Folder 15)
    - Desert Dispute: research materials: Qatar Boundaries (FCO 8/733), 1967-1968 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Desert Dispute: research materials: Qatar Boundaries (FCO 8/734), 1967-1968 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Desert Dispute: research materials: Qatar Boundaries (FCO 8/735), 1967-1968 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Desert Dispute: research materials: Trucial States. Frontiers (FCO 8/853, FCO 8/857, FCO 8/965, FO 371 / 174706), 1967-1969 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Desert Dispute: research materials: Trucial States. Frontiers (FCO 8/964), 1967-1969 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Desert Dispute: research materials: Muscat and Oman. Boundaries (FCO 8/1083), 1968-1969 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Desert Dispute: research materials: Saudi claims to territory in Abu Dhabi (FCO 8/1332), 1970 (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Desert Dispute: research materials: (FCO 8/1339), 1970 (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Desert Dispute: research materials: (FC) 8/1340), 1970 (Box 30, Folder 9)
    - Desert Dispute: research materials: Extensions of territorial boundaries in the Gulf (FCO 8/1342), 1970 (Box 30, Folder 10)
    - Desert Dispute: research materials: Saudi - South Yemen border (FCO 8/1455), 1970 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Desert Dispute: research materials: Qatar-Saudi boundaries (FCO 8/1474), 1970-1971 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Desert Dispute: research materials: Saudi Arabia claims to disputed territory... (FCO 8/1614), 1971 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Desert Dispute: research materials: Saudi claims to territory in Abu Dhabi (FCO 8/1615), 1971 (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - Desert Dispute: research materials: Saudi claims to territory in Abu Dhabi (FCO 8/1616), 1971 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Desert Dispute: research materials: Oman - Trucial States fronter (FCO 8/1773), 1971 (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Desert Dispute: research materials: Saudi claims to territory in Abu Dhabi and Oman (FCO 8/1813), 1972 (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - Desert Dispute: research materials: Boundaries between Oman and Saudi Arabia (FCO 8/2223), 1974 (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - Desert Dispute: research materials: PDRY-Oman boundaries (FCO 8/2952), 1979 (Box 31, Folder 9)
    - Book reviews: reviews by M.E. Yapp of works by J.B. Kelly (Box 31, Folder 10)
  - Other: essays, interviews, lectures and miscellaneous writings
    - "Britain's Imperial Legacy in the Middle East," undated, unidentified publication. (Box 31, Folder 11)
    - Saudi Arabia clippings, 1956-1960 (Box 31, Folder 12)
    - Lectures: general, 1961-1975 and undated (Box 31, Folder 13)
    - Chatham House Discussion Group: Britain and the Persian Gulf (1), 1964 (Box 31, Folder 14)
    - Chatham House Discussion Group: Britain and the Persian Gulf (2), 1964 (Box 31, Folder 15)
    - Chatham House Discussion Group: Britain and the Persian Gulf (3), 1964 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - Chatham House Discussion Group: Britain and the Persian Gulf (4), 1964 (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Conference: Princeton University Conference on Middle East Focus: the Persian Gulf. Commentary by J.B. Kelly on another paper by Robert Geren Landen, 1968 (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - Lecture: "T.E. Lawrence and His Friends," [unidentified, perhaps Univ. of Wisconsin, 1968] (Box 32, Folder 4)
    - Response to BBC television series, "The British Empire," including letter to The Times, and correspondence with Jan Morris, 1972 (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - Harvard Studies on the African Diaspora: correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 32, Folder 6)
    - Letters to editor: general, 1974-1988 (Box 32, Folder 7)
    - Articles and letters: Daily Telegraph, 1975 (Box 32, Folder 8)
    - Letters to The Times (London), regarding Lebanon, 1976 (Box 32, Folder 9)
    - Articles: Encyclopaedia of Islam (Brill): drafts of articles and editorial correspondence, 1976-1979 (Box 32, Folder 10)
    - Articles: Encyclopaedia of Islam (Brill): reprints of articles authored by JBK, 1976-1979 (Box 32, Folder 11)
    - Exchange in Middle East Review regarding response to review of "Anglo-Arab Labyrinth" (Kedourie), 1977 (Box 32, Folder 12)
    - Symposia/conferences: "The Security of Middle East Oil," Institute for the Study of Conflict (London), May 1979 (Box 32, Folder 13)
    - "Inside OPEC," Episode #431, Firing Line (Willam F. Buckley), broadcast date, 09-28-1980 (Box 32, Folder 14)
    - "Islam Through the Looking Glass," lecture at Heritage Foundation, Washington, DC, 1980 (Box 32, Folder 15)
    - Interview: "Die OPEC ist kein Monolith," Integral, no. 9/81, 1981 (Box 32, Folder 16)
    - Interview: "La base du Golfe," Valeurs Actuelles, 10-04-1981 (Box 32, Folder 17)
    - Excerpt from "Arabia, the Gulf, and the West," reprinted in "Saudi Arabia: American Friend or Foe?" no attribution, circa 1981 (Box 32, Folder 18)
    - "The Arming of Saudi Arabia," paper presented at Woodrow Wilson Center, October 1981 (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Interview of J.B. Kelly by Brigitte Ades, for unidentified French publication, undated, circa 1981 (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - Archive Editions: correspondence, 1986 (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - Cambridge University Press: editorial correspondence and draft texts of reviews, 1986-1988 (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - "Jeux san frontieres: Philby's travels in Southern Arabia," essay in Bernard Lewis festschrift, Princeton University, folder 1, 1988 (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - "Jeux san frontieres: Philby's travels in Southern Arabia," essay in Bernard Lewis festschrift, Princeton University, folder 2, 1988-1990 (Box 33, Folder 6)
    - "Arabian Frontiers and Anglo-American Relations" (1991), lecture at LSE, published in "Government and Opposition" (Box 33, Folder 7)
- Research materials
  - Archives, lists of records: Public Records Office: Foreign Office, Colonial Office (Box 33, Folder 8)
  - Archives, lists of records: India Office Records (Box 33, Folder 9)
  - Archives, lists of records: United Kingdom: other repositories (Box 33, Folder 10)
  - Archives, lists of records: United States: other repositories (Box 33, Folder 11)
  - Archives, U.S.: Dwight D. Eisenhower Presidential Library (Box 33, Folder 12)
  - Archives, U.S.: Harry S Truman Presidential Library (Box 33, Folder 13)
  - "British Commonwealth," folder 1, 1953 (Box 33, Folder 14)
  - "British Commonwealth," folder 2, 1953 (Box 33, Folder 15)
  - "British Commonwealth," folder 3, 1953 (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Aden Protectorate, 1956 (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Aden Protectorate affairs, 1935-1939 (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Aden/Saudi Arabia Frontier, 1956-1966. Aden/Oman Frontier, 1956-1966. Oil Exploration. (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Arbitration: - Tribunal Sittings. - Saudi Breaches of Agreement, 1955 (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - Anglo-American Relations, Jan-July. Anglo-Saudi Relations: II Frontiers Issue, 1952 (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - 1) ARAMCO's Agreements with S.A. 2) Territorial Waters/Offshore Boundaries. 3) Ibn Saud/FDR Photos, 1945 (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Buckmaster's Report on Liwa, 1952 (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Buraimi and the Dhahirah/Trucial Oman, October - December. Sultan, Imam and Saudis. (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - Buraimi documents: discovered correspondence (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - Buraimi: Miscellaneous (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - Desert Zone / Rainbow Collection / Saudi Frontier Claim, April 1935 (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - Dhufar/South Western Frontiers. State Department Records (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - Frontier Question, 1958-1961 (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - Frontier Question, 1962, 1964-1965 (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - Gulf, Miscellaneous, 1945 (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - Hadramaut/Italy, 1935-1939 (Box 36, Folder 6)
  - Hinterland boundaries of Aden Protectorate (Hadhramaut), 1934-1935 (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - London Conference, 1951 (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - London Talks, June - July. The Murra Dar (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - Maps: [Violet Line boundary] (Box OS 1)
  - Oil operations and Southeast Frontiers, 1946-1948 (Box 37, Folder 4)
  - Oman: Sultanate and Imamate, 1956 (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - Oman and Dhufar. P.C.L. Exploration/Extent of Sultan's Authority, 1946-1949 (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - Qatar frontier (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Reconsideration of Policy, December 1952 (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Reoccupation of Buraimi and its Aftermath, September - December 1955 (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - Reopening of Frontier Question, 1949 (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - Saudi Arabia: Frontier Question, 1956 (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - Saudi Zakat Collections: Trucial Oman, 1925-1930 (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - S.E. Frontiers: Wartime Discussions, 1940-1946 (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - Territorial Waters (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - Thomas / Philby: crossing of the Rub al Khali (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - Tribes/Muscat Authority: Reports, 1950-1954 (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - Uqair frontier, 1922; Al Hasa oil concession, 1922-1923 (Box 39, Folder 6)
  - Western Abu Dhabi: material collected, 1951 (Box 39, Folder 7)
  - 1933-1934: Qatar Oil Concession: The Qatar Frontier I (Box 39, Folder 8)
  - 1934/I: Qatar Frontier II, U.S. Blue Line Enquiry (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - 1934/II: Notification of Blue Line Policy Discussions, May - September (Box 40, Folder 2)
  - 1934/III: Investigations East of Blue Line - (September to December) (1) (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - 1934/IV: Investigations East of Blue Line - (September to December) (2) (Box 40, Folder 4)
  - 1935/III: The Genesis of the Riyad Line, September - November (Box 40, Folder 5)
  - 1936: Qatar, Aden, Oman Frontiers (Box 41, Folder 1)
  - 1936-1939: Oil company activities: Trucial Oman, Sultanate of Oman (Box 41, Folder 2)
  - 1937-1938: Frontiers: Jiddah Negotiations / Sufuq Wells / Oman / CASOC Activities (Box 41, Folder 3)
  - 1938-1939: Frontiers: Jabal Nakhsh/Khaur Al Udaid (Box 41, Folder 4)
  - 1950: Anglo Saudi Frontier Negotiations (Box 41, Folder 5)
  - 1950: Oman and Buraimi (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - 1951: Central Oman/Buraimi (Box 42, Folder 2)
  - 1951: Anglo-Saudi Frontier Negotiations, January - July (Box 42, Folder 3)
  - 1951/1952: Dammam Conference Preliminaries/Aftermath (Box 42, Folder 4)
  - 1952: Anglo-Saudi Negotiations after Standstill (Box 42, Folder 5)
  - 1952: Buraimi Shaikhs: P.C.L. and Muscat Authority. Saudi Claims to Authority. (Box 42, Folder 6)
  - 1952: Qatar Frontier/Miscellaneous. 1954: Oil Operations (Box 42, Folder 7)
  - 1952: Saudi Occupation of Hamasa. Standstill Agreement. (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - 1953: Anglo-Saudi-American Negotiations July-December (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - 1953: Buraimi Oasis and Environs (Box 43, Folder 3)
  - 1953: Denunciation of Status Quo, 1951/Standstill Agreements, 1952. (Box 43, Folder 4)
  - 1953: Negotiations Towards Arbitration, April - July (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - 1953/1954: Aden Protectorate/Saudi Arabia Frontier Dhufar/ Aden Protectorate Frontier ARAMCO Exploration. (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - 1954: Arbitration Negotiations, Oil Concessions/Operations (Box 44, Folder 3)
  - 1954: Events at Buraimi/Bani Ka'ab Abu Dhabi/ Interior of Oman (Duru and Ibri) (Box 44, Folder 4)
  - 1954: Visit of Red Cross Rep to Hamasa (Buraimi) (Box 44, Folder 5)
  - 1955: Sultanate, Imamate, Saudi Arabia: Extension of Sultan's Authority (Box 45, Folder 1)
  - State Department Records: Frontier, 1949-1950 (Box 45, Folder 2)
  - State Department Records: Frontier, 1951-1952 (Box 45, Folder 3)
  - State Department Records: Frontier, 1953 (Box 45, Folder 4)
  - State Department Records: Frontier, 1954 (Folder 46, Folder 1)
  - Iran and Oil (typescript notes from articles in The Times), 1951 (Folder 46, Folder 2)
  - Persian claims to Bahrain (handwritten notes) (Folder 46, Folder 3)
  - India Office Records: various notes (Folder 46, Folder 4)
  - Bombay Marine, Indian Navy, Royal Navy (note cards) (Folder 46, Folder 5)
  - Indian Empire in the 20th century (notes from published sources), folder 1 (Folder 46, Folder 6)
  - Indian Empire in the 20th century (notes from published sources), folder 2 (Folder 46, Folder 7)
  - Persian Gulf - Turkish jurisdiction along the Arabian Coast (copied doc from I.O.R., P+S Correspondence, vol. 34) (Folder 46, Folder 8)
  - Legal briefs, U.S. Court of Appeals, 75-3088, Occidental of Umm al Qaywayn, inc. vs. Cities Service Oil Co., et.al., 1975-1978 (Folder 46, Folder 9)
  - Persian Gulf: news clippings and other material, 1981-1983 (Box 47, Folder 1)
  - Saudi Arabia: clippings, 1981-1983 (Box 47, Folder 2)
- Maps [closed pending processing]